Guide to the Ralph I. Gifford Photographs circa 1910s - 1947
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
- Postcard Photographs, circa 1935-1945; Series VI; 58 prints and 57 negatives
  - South Falls - Winter - Silver Falls Park, Oregon, PC #172; 2 5x7 copy negatives (Box 63)
  - South Falls - Winter - Silver Falls Park, Oregon, PC #173; 2 prints and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Wallowa Lake, Oregon, PC #172; postcard print and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Eagle Cap - Glacier Lake, Wallowa Mountains, Oregon, PC #173; 2 printd and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - On trail below Frazier Lake, Wallowa Mountains, Oregon, PC #174; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Reflections, Moccasin Lake, Wallowa Mts., Oregon, PC #175; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Moccasin Lake - Wallowa Mts., Oregon, PC #181; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Glacier Lake - Wallowa Mountains, Oregon, PC #182; postcard print and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Sunrise on Eagle Cap, Wallowa, Oregon, PC #183; 4 5x7 copy negatives (Box 63)
  - Wallowa Lake, Oregon (people by lake), PC #187; 2 prints and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Wallowa Lake, Oregon (boat in lake), PC #188; 2 prints and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Herefords, Wallowa Valley, PC #189; 2 prints and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Wallowa River, Oregon, PC #190; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Cutting clover, Wallowa Valley, Oregon, PC #191; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Cutting clover, Wallowa Valley, Oregon, PC #192; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Snake River Canyon, Oregon, PC #193; 2 prints and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Wallowa Lake basin country, Oregon, PC #194; 5x7 copy negative (Box 63)
  - Crooked River Gorge, Oregon, PC #197; print and 5x7 copy negative (Box 3, 63)
  - Caption negatives for postcards, 6 negatives strips and 1 8x10 negative (Box 63, 69)
  - Scenic Oregon Album Prints, booklet of 10 prints (Box 3)
    Album of 3.5x4.5 prints. Includes images of the State Capitol Building in Salem, Oregon; Vista House and the Columbia River Gorge; sunset from Corwn Point on the Columbia River Highway; Timberline Lodge at Mt. Hood, Oregon; blossom time in the Hood River Valley; a western sunset on the Oregon coast; fishing boats in Depoe Bay on the Oregon coast; the Crooked River Gorge near Bend; and Wizard Island and Phantom Ship at Crater Lake, Oregon.
- Coastal Bridges, circa 1936; Series VII; 20 negatives and 1 print
  Series VII consists of photographs of bridges along Highway 101 on the Oregon coast that were designed by Conde McCullough. All of the images are 8x10 film negatives; the series includes a print of only one image. Several of the negatives have a diacetate base that is shrinking or exhibiting other deterioration; these negatives have been separated and are stored separately.
  - Alsea Bay Bridge, Waldport, Oregon, in final stages of construction, B-A-1 thru B-A-3; 3 8x10 negatives (Box 69)
  - McCullough Memorial Bridge, North Bend, Oregon, over Coos Bay; final stages of construction, B-C-1 thru B-C-6; 6 8x10 negatives (Box 69)
    - B-C-1, print and 8x10 negative (Box 3, 69)
    - B-C-2 thru B-C-6, 5 8x10 negatives (Box 75)
  - Siuslaw Bridge, Florence, Oregon, B-S-1 thru B-S-2
    - B-S-1, 3 8x10 negatives (Box 69, 75)
    - B-S-2, 8x10 negative (Box 75)
  - Umpqua Bridge, Reedsport, Oregon, B-U-1 thru B-U-4
    - B-U-1, 8x10 negative (Box 75)
    - B-U-3, 8x10 negative (Box 75)
    - B-U-2 and B-U-4, 2 8x10 negatives (Box 75)
  - Yaquina Bay Bridge, Newport, Oregon, under construction, B-Y; B-Y-1; B-Y-2; 3 8x10 negatives (Box 69)
- Un-Numbered Photographs, circa 1935 - 1947; Series VIII; 279 negatives and 128 prints
  Series VIII consists of photographs made by Gifford throughout Oregon during the 1930s and 1940s that were not assigned individual item numbers. Many of the images are of Oregon landmarks and scenes that are also depicted in other series. The series includes views of the Oregon Coast; Mount Hood and other Cascade Mountain peaks; Crater Lake; Oregon Caves; Silver Falls State Park; the Oregon State Capitol and other Salem, Oregon, scenes; and sport fishing. Of special note are images of the Pendleton Round-Up, including photographs of Native Americans participating in Round-Up activities.. The series includes 4x5, 5x7 and 8x10 camera negatives, many of which do not have accompanying prints, as well as prints with no accompanying negatives.
  - Herd of sheep with one black sheep in middle (Box 4)
  - Herd of sheep on pasture; black sheep near front of herd (Box 4)
  - Ralph I. Gifford's Birth Certificate, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - View of road next to railroad tracks, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Fisherman leaning back in boat to land fish, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Traffic interchange at Union Avenue, Denver Avenue, and Swift Boulevard in Portland, Oregon, 4 prints (Box 4)
    Photograph of drawing by Oregon State Highway Commission engineer and images of models.
  - Oregon Caves
    - Two women exploring the caves; one leaning over railing, 3 prints and 5x7 negative (Box 4, 63)
    - Women on formation in cave, 3 prints and 5x7 negative (Box 4, 63)
    - Women standing on formation in cave, 4 prints and 5x7 negative (Box 4, 63)
    - Women on walkway in Oregon Caves, 2 prints and 5x7 negative (Box 4, 63)
  - Highway crew at Mt. Hood when Ralph worked up there, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Mt. Jefferson and North Santiam River, 4 prints and 9 4x5 negatives (Box 4, 8)
    Nine different views.
  - Gifford logos and captions
    - 4x5 negative and print (Box 4, 8)
    - 4 5x7 negatives and 1 8x10 negative (Box 63, 69)
  - An orchard with cliffs in the background, print and 4x5 negative (Box 4, 8)
  - Country road through orchards in bloom, 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - Cows in a field, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Ocean cove surrounded by rocks, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Paper pulp plant on the Willamette River at Oregon City, print and 4x5 negative (Box 4, 8)
  - Man fishing, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Mt. Hood; Timberline lodge in the snow, 4 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Beth Greenlee and her Jersey calf in orchard of cherry blossoms, 6 prints and 8 4x5 negatives (Box 4, 8)
  - Little deer, Timberline Lodge?, 2 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Neskowin job; state map, 2 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - McKenzie River Guides, 15 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Brookings, Beaulieu Houses, 7 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Highway interchange (Union, Denver, and Swift) near Vancouver Bridge, Portland, 3 prints (Box 4)
  - Construction of Union, Denver, and Swift interchange near Vancouver Bridge, Portland, and Gault Boat Works, 15 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Beach shots made by Ralph Gifford; Ben and Beth?
    - 41 4x5 negatives and 3 5x7 copy negatives (Box 8, 63)
    - 5 prints (Box 4)
  - Beach at Seaside, circa 1940; 3 prints (Box 4)
    One image available online.
  - Beach below Neahkahnie Mountain north of Tillamook (Box 4)
    State Highway Commission photo.
  - Coastal sand dunes, 7 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
    Near Florence?
  - Pendleton Round-Up, circa 1940; 13 prints and 33 3x4 and 4x5 negatives (Box 4, 8)
    Include Native American in traditional costumes, rodeo events, and other activities.
    - Cowboys and cow girl in Pendleton Round-Up parade
    - Cowgirl at the Pendleton Round-Up
    - Man on a bucking horse at the Pendleton Round-Up
    - Native Americans in Early Ox cart, Pendleton Round-Up Parade
    - Prospector with donkey at Pendleton Round-up
    - Ox team and covered wagon
    - Chief Clarence Burke
    - Chief Clarence Burke of the Umatilla Indians on horseback
    - Chief Clarence Burke awarding dance prizes
    - Indian woman and child on horseback
    - Indian women racing on horseback
    - Native Americans in ceremonial regalia
    - Indian women view ceremonial dance
    - Native American dancers at Pendleton Round-Up
    - Child on horseback in front of tipi
    - Older woman and child watching festivities
    - Chief Clarence Burke and others watching events at the Pendleton Round-Up
  - House on a hill, circa 1938; 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Golden Falls, 3 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Silver Falls on the Coos River, 3 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - River Boat Graveyard, Coquille River, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Snow geysers, 2 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
    Snow clearing on mountain roads.
  - Man on horseback, 2 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Beach at Cape San Sebastian, one print and 2 4x5 negatives (Box 4, 8)
    One of the images is Oregon Highway Division #6485.
  - Heceta Head Lighthouse, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Heceta Head campfire (Box 4)
  - Ocean cliff; boats in water in distance, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Unidentified building, May 7, 1944; 4x5 negative (Box 8)
    State office complex in Salem?
  - Men net fishing on platforms, Celilo Falls, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Ben and Beth Gifford's wedding, 17 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Bear Creek Lodge, 1940; 7 prints and 6 4x5 negatives (Box 4, 8)
  - Fly fishing on the Metolius River, print and 2 4x5 negatives (Box 4, 8)
  - Oregon State Highway Commission sign at entrance to Van Duzer Forest Corridor, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Old Oregon Trail sign on Columbia River Highway, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Gorge on the Imnaha River, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Unidentified river gorge, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Crooked River gorge?, 3 4x5 negatives (Box 8)
  - Snake River Gorge?, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Fossil beds on the John Day River?, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Multnomah Falls, 5x7 copy negative of an 8x10 color transparency (Box 63)
  - Pasture and Mt. Hood, 2 5x7 negatives (Box 63)
  - Eaton Hall, Willamette University, 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - E.S. Collins Hall, Willamette University, print and 5x7 negative (Box 4, 63)
  - State Capitol Building, print and 2 5x7 negatives (Box 4, 63)
  - Art gallery and gift shop, 5 5x7 negatives (Box 63)
  - Silver Falls State Park, 3 prints and 2 5x7 negatives (Box 4, 63)
    Four views of foot bridges and picnic shelters.
  - The Nook Cafe, Brookings, Oregon, 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - Side view of a house; car in driveway, 1942; 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - Three women at base of waterfall, 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - Woman standing at gate to orchard, 2 5x7 negatives (Box 63)
  - Man and woman standing in an orchard in bloom, 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - Man and woman looking at large trees in a forest, 5x7 negative (Box 63)
  - Views of plowed fields, 3 5x7 negative and 1 8x10 negative (Box 63, 69)
  - Man and prize horses, 4 5x7 negatives (Box 62)
    Numbered 8-12, 8-14, 8-16, & 8-20
  - Ocean sunset, 2 5x7 negatives (Box 62)
  - Orchard with Mt. Hood in background, 5x7 negative (Box 62)
  - Copies of Arthur A. Selander's etchings, 12 5x7 negatives (Box 62)
  - A picture of Neskowin Golf Course, Neskowin, Oregon, 2 5x7 negatives (Box 62)
  - Men working on a farm with steam powered equipment, 2 5x7 negatives (Box 62)
  - A couple at the beach, 5x7 copy negative (Box 62)
  - Three men, 2 5x7 copy negatives (Box 62)
    Two military officers and a civilian.
  - Arlington? Cubs baseball team, June 1915; 5x7 copy negative (Box 62)
  - Man taking photo of family on side of highway; Mt. Hood in background, print and 8x10 negative (Box 4, 69)
    Oregon State Highway Commission photograph.
  - Highway and Mt. Hood, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Unidentified lake and mountains, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Man and woman with boat on shore holding caught fish, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Climbers scaling cliff above road and river, 2 8x10 negatives (Box 69)
  - Three people gazing at mountains from hillside, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Unidentified buildings at night, 8x10 negative (Box 69)
  - Wagon going through surf on coast, copy print and 8x10 copy negative (Box 4, 69)
  - Island in Columbia River (Box 4)
  - Tumalo Falls (Box 4)
  - Fisherman fly fishing at base of Tumalo Falls, oversize print (Box 74)
  - Man fly fishing in lake; Three Sisters in background, oversize mounted print (Box 74)
  - Woman sitting on rock next to lake; mountain in background (Box 4)
  - Two girls sitting near base of a waterfall (Box 4)
  - Preview of Silver Creek Falls Lodge opening and 1st banquet, May 27, 1947; 3 prints (Box 4)
  - Wizard Island, Crater Lake, 2 prints (Box 4)
  - Crater Lake, 8 prints (Box 4)
    Caldera rim; Phantom Ship; boats in the lake; Wizard Island.
  - Fishing off the mouth of the Columbia River, Oregon, 2 prints (Box 4)
  - Man fishing on Todd Lake; Broken Top in the background (Box 4)
  - Man fishing in a river (Alsea River?) (Box 4)
  - Man fishing near sunset (Box 4)
  - Fisherman landing fish, 2 prints (Box 4)
    2 views
  - Two men and Wanda Gifford with boat in river, 2 prints (Box 4)
  - Two men with boat in river (Box 4)
  - Man fly fishing (Box 4)
  - Man in a rowboat with a trolling line (Box 4)
  - Three men fishing from a boat on a fast moving river (Box 4)
  - Catch of fish, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Dehooking a fish, 4x5 negative (Box 8)
  - Group eating dinner, October 1946 (Box 4)
  - State Capitol in Salem, print (Box 4)
    Print is labeled #1144; framed oversize print on exhibit.
  - Sicks' Brewing Company, Salem, Oregon, 6 prints (Box 4)
  - Portrait of Governor Earl Snell, print and oversize print (Box 4, 73)
  - Portrait of Billie Smith of Salem, Oregon (Box 4)
  - Portrait of a young woman (Box 4)
  - Highway underpass, Bend, Oregon (Box 4)
  - Highway being paved at Oregon-California state line (Box 4)
  - Group baling hay, 2 prints (Box 4)
  - Ralph Gifford with dog and horse (Box 4)
  - Man with two dogs viewing Snake River Gorge, oversize print (Box 73)
  - Family viewing Columbia River Gorge, hand-colored oversize print (Box 74)
  - Dairy cattle going through a gate, oversize print (Box 74)
  - Sailboats on Columbia River?, mounted blue-toned oversize print (Box 74)
  - Photo poster advertisement for the Chemeketans (Salem Hiking Club), Climbing High and Traveling the Trails, 3 oversize prints (Box 74)
    Includes photographs of a mountain climber.
- Color Transparencies, circa 1937 - 1947; Series IX; 56 color transparencies and 1 print
  Series IX consists of color transparencies of various Oregon scenes; many of the views are similar to black-and-white images in other series. Subjects include Mount Hood and other Cascade Mountain peaks; Crater Lake; the Oregon Coast; the Wallowa Mountains; the Columbia River Gorge; and the Oregon State Capitol and other buildings in Salem. Of special note is an image of Chief Clarence Burke. Many of the images are available online. Most of the transparencies are 4x5 inches; however there are several 5x7 and 8x10 transparencies included. Two of the 4x5 transparencies are mounted in glass. A color print of one of the images is included.
  - State Capitol Building soon after construction, circa 1937; 4x5 color transparency mounted in glass (Box 64)
  - Champoeg mural in Oregon House of Representatives, State Capitol, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also image 0763 in Series IV.
  - Circuit Rider, Statuary in Capitol Park, Salem, Oregon, 5x7 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Marion County Courthouse, circa 1940; 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - U.S. Post Office, Salem, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - State office building, Salem, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Ferry on the Willamette River, circa 1937; 4x5 color transparency mounted in glass (Box 64)
  - Lily field, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Oregon holly which grows so abundantly in the Pacific Northwest, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Rhododendron bloom, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Waves crashing on rocks, Oregon Coast, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Haystack rocks, Oregon Coast, 8x10 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Wild azaleas on the Oregon Coast, 2 8x10 color transparencies (Box 68)
  - Heceta Head Lighthouse, 2479; 8x10 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Sand dunes near Florence, Oregon, not far from Highway 101, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Billie Smith of Salem at the Oregon coast, 3 4x5 color transparencies (Box 64)
  - Golden Falls on the Coos River, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Oregon coast taken from Highway 101 near Brookings, Oregon, print and 4x5 color transparency (Box 4, 64)
  - Fish On; Mt. Washington and Big Lake on the Santiam Highway, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also images 0794 and 0848 in Series IV.
  - Rod, basket and fish, 1492; 5x7 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Hunter on edge of the Deschutes River, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Hunters eating breakfast in Central or Eastern Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - On road to Bend with view of Three Sisters Mountains, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Autumn on road to Bend, Oregon, 2471; 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Middle and North sister from The Dalles-California Highway near Redmond, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Crater Lake, 2477; 8x10 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Woman viewing Crater Lake, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Woman viewing Wizard Island, Crater Lake, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - The Phantom Ship, Crater Lake, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Stacked lumber, Klamath Falls, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also image 0704 in Series IV.
  - Little girl lands one (fish) from beneath a log raft, Southern Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Multnomah Falls, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Multnomah Falls, Columbia River Highway; parking lot and lodge, 8x10 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Mushroom Rock near Shepherd's Dell, Columbia River Highway, Oregon, 8x10 color transparency (Box 68)
  - View of log floats on the Columbia River from the highway, 5x7 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Pear blossoms; Mt. Hood in distance, 5x7 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Oregon Grape, Hood River Valley; Mt. Hood in distance, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Mt. Hood and rhododendrons in bloom in June, 2 4x5 color transparencies (Box 64)
    One of the images is numbered 2469; this image is available online.
  - Hood River Valley and Mt. Hood, 2478; 8x10 color transparency (Box 68)
  - Mt. Hood from Big Eddy, The Dalles, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also image 0837 in Series IV.
  - Mt. Hood and Hood Canal near The Dalles, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Shocked oat field; Mt. Hood in distance, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also image 0722 in Series IV.
  - Chief Clarence Burke, Pendleton, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    At the Pendleton Round-Up?
  - Mowing clover in the Wallowa Valley near Enterprise, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also postcards (PC) #191 and #192 in Series VI.
  - Clover field in full bloom in the Wallowa Valley near Enterprise, Oregon, 2 4x5 color transparencies (Box 64)
  - White faced Herefords on the Wallowa River near Enterprise, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also postcard (PC) #189 in Series VI.
  - Wallowa Lake, taken from just above the highway, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Packing In; Glacier Lake in the Wallowa Mountains, Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
    See also image 0792 in Series IV.
  - Snake River Canyon in the northeastern part of Oregon, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Deserted House, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)
  - Eastern Oregon sunset, 4x5 color transparency (Box 64)